A Guide to the Richmond (Va.), Bureau of Permits and Inspections, Building permit architectural blueprints and specifications, 1907-1976
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Richmond (Va.), Bureau of Permits and Inspections, Building permit architectural blueprints, 1907-1950
Library of Virginia
30150, 30745, 38536
3167 sets of blueprints.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restriction:Due to the light sensitive and fragile nature of the blueprinte, researchers are directed to use the microfilm verison of this material.Paper copies of the architectural blueprints are served only when they have not been microfilmed or circumstances dictate use of the original. See Archives Reference Staff for assistance.
Acquisition Information
Copies of plans and specifications, 1922-1924 came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of records from City of Richmond's Commissioner of Buildings in 1978 under accession 30150.
Building plans, 1925-1982 came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of records from City of Richmond's Commissioner of Buildings in 1979 under accession 30745.
Building plans, 1907-1955, came to the Library of Virginia in a transfer of records from ity of Richmond, Department of Community Development, Bureau of Permits and Inspections in 1979 under accession under accession 38536.
Building permits and architectural drawngs, lent to the LIbrary of Virginia for microfilming from City of Richmond, Department of Community Development, Bureau of Permits and Inspections, on 28 March 2000 under accession 37533.
Historical Information
Context for Records: Beginning in 1908, the City of Richmond instituted a policy of issuing formal building permits. Along with an application for a building permit, part of the process for approval of a building was the submission of a set of architectural blueprints and written specifications for the proposed project. These applications were submitted to the Richmond City Office of Building Inspection which was responsible for the review of the drawings and the issuing of building permits.
Locality History: The city of Richmond, located between Henrico and Chesterfield Counties, was named by William Byrd (1674-1744), who envisioned the development of a city at the falls of the James River and with the help of William Mayo laid out the town in 1737. The name probably came from the English borough of Richmond upon Thames, which Byrd visited on several occasions. Richmond was established in 1742 and in 1779 was designated the capital of Virginia effective 30 April 1780. It was incorporated as a town, although "stiled the city of Richmond," in 1782 and was incorporated as a city in 1842. It served as the capital of the Confederacy from mid-1861 to April 1865. Richmond was enlarged by the annexation of Manchester (or South Richmond) in 1910, and by the addition of Barton Heights, Fairmount, and Highland Park in 1914. Further annexations from Chesterfield County occurred in 1942 and 1970.
Scope and Content
Richmond (Va.), Bureau of Permits and Inspections, Building permit architectural blueprints, 1907-1950, consists of building permit applications, architectural blueprints, and specifications for construction of and alterations to structures in the City of Richmond, Virginia, from 1907-1950. The structures documented include apartment buildings, banks, churches, commercial buildings, fraternal society buildings, garages, hospitals, hotels, municipal and state government buildings, office buildings, schools, service stations, single and multi-family residences, synagogues, and the like. Permit application forms may include some or all of the following information: name of applicant, architect, builder, construction materials, cost of construction, dimensions of the structure, and the race of the occupant.
Accessions 30150, 30745, and 38536 are the surviving paper blueprints, 1907-1949, from the Richmond City Office of Building Inspection. The materials are organized by a control number assigned during processing. Paper copies of the architectural blueprints are served only when they have not been microfilmed or circumstances dictate use of the original. Surviving building specifications have been rolled with the architectural blueprints.
Arrangement
Series 1: Blueprint drawings, 1907-1950
Contents List
- Blueprint drawings, 1907-1950, 3167 sets of blueprints
  Accessions 30150, 30745, and 38536 are arranged numerically by their Library of Virginia control number. This number was imposed on the collection due to inconsistencies in the permit numbers.
  Accessions 30150, 30745, and 38536 are the surviving paper blueprints, 1907-1949, from the Richmond City Office of Building Inspection. The materials are organized by a control number assigned during processing. Paper copies of the architectural blueprints are served only when they have not been microfilmed or circumstances dictate use of the original. Surviving building specifications have been rolled with the architectural blueprints.
  - Apartments, 1907-1948
    loosely chronological
    Bluepprint of aparment buildings in Richmond (Va.). Generally contatins permit number; street address; date; name of architiect who drew the blueprints; name of contractor; number of commissioner of the work; and additional notes.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 302, Apartment House for W. A. Chesterman, Esq., Address: SW corner of Harrison and Franklin Sts., 1907 (Folder 208)
      Drawn by: Aubrey Chesterman, Architect, Lynchburg, Virginia; Contractor: N/A; Commissioned by: W. A. Chesterman; Notes: 2-story over basemen, brick apartment house designed in the Renaissance revival (American) style. 3 apartments per floor which include 2 chambers, a parlor and a dining room, kitchen, pantry, and full bath. The basement plan includes a drug store, barber shop, 2 offices, 2 storage rooms, a billiard room, a boiler room, and a fuel room. Extant building (3/2000).
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 839, Flat Building for A. L. Phillips, Esq., Address: N. side Monument Ave. between Alison & Addison Sts., 1908 (Folder 166)
      Drawn by: W. Leigh Carneal, Architect, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: L. C. Jenkins; Commissioned by: A. L. Phillips; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 828, Flat Building for Mr. L. Sycle, Address: 2007 Monument Ave., 1908 (Folder 84)
      Drawn by: W. Leigh Carneal, Architect, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: Quarles and Palmer; Commissioned by: Mina L Sycle; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 894, Three-Story Flat Building (brick) for Mrs. Edw. R. Fuller, Address: Allen Ave. between Monument and Park Aves.,, 1908 (Folder 100)
      Drawn by: Carl Ruehrmund, Architect, 918 E. Main Street, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: George D. Priddy; Commissioned by: Mrs. Edward R. Fuller; Notes: Carl Ruehrmund is best known for his downtown-Richmond commercial work. His most ambitious project in the Fan was The Shenandoah (1906), a high rise apartment house located on Allen Avenue across the street from what was then The Jefferson Club. His drawing conventions are different from those of his contemporaries. He does not usually title or date each sheet, and may use odd-shaped paper, as is the case with these plans. The builder, George D. Priddy built many structures in the Fan. He worked under contract for architects, owners, and developers alike. His foreman in 1910 was Henry C. Smith, who was also a draftsman This is a 3-story brick apartment building with a full basement. The front elevation shows a flat roof, two entrances, and neo-classical ornament such as urn-finials and standard Ionic columns. The first floor plan shows a parlor, library, dining room, kitchen, full bath, and four undesignated rooms. The second and third floors are identical to the first. There is a full utility basement.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 744, Apartment House for W. A. Chesterman Esq., Franklin and Adams Streets, Address: 100 W. Franklin St., 1908 (Folder 165)
      Drawn by: Aubrey Chesterman, Architect, Lynchburg, Va.; Contractor: N/A; Commissioned by: W. A. Chesterman; Notes: Three additional sheets titled "Revised Plan of Hanover Apartments." are dated July 1908.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1383, Apartment Building for Mrs. Barton H. Wise, Address: S/S Franklin St., corner of Harrison, 1909 (Folder 6)
      Drawn by: Noland & Baskervill; Contractor: D. B. Slaughter; Commissioned by: Mrs. Barton H. Wise; Notes: See Permit no. 1121A, 1/28/1910. Three-story brick apartment building with one apartment on each floor. Each four-bedroom apartment [three bedrooms on first floor to accommodate entry] includes two servant's rooms and dining facilities, a reception hall, parlor, and library.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1150, Gresham Court, Address: N. side Franklin St. [Torn], 1909 (Folder 3)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: W. A Chester[man]; Commissioned by: NA; Notes: The blueprints are particularly fragile. Typical Floor has four apartments off a main corridor with central stair and elevator. Average apartment includes two bedrooms in addition to a servant's room accessible to one of two shared side stairs. The first floor apartments do not have kitchen or dining facilities. There are dining rooms, additional servant's rooms, and a drugstore in the basement.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1089, Flat Building for Mr. M. Mitteldorfer, Address: 212 E. Grace St., 1909 (Folder 10)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: Geo. D. Priddy; Commissioned by: D & E Mitteldorfer; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2320, Apartments for Miss Rosa Hexter, Address: N. side Monument Ave. between Boulevard and Deep Run St., 1910 (Folder 170)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: W. S. Quarles; Commissioned by: Miss Rosa Hexter; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1495, Flats for Mrs. S. W. Sutherland, Address: Corner of Allen and Park Aves.., 1910 (Folder 205)
      Drawn by: Charles M. Fisher Co., Architects and Engineers, 123 East Broad Street, Richmond; Contractor: N/A; Commissioned by: Mrs. S. W. Sutherland; Notes: Brick, 3-story over basement building containing 3 identical flats. Floor plan = Entrance hall, parlor, 3 chambers, full bath, servant room, kit., dining room, pantry, trunk room, and store room. Front elevation is Colonial Revival in style with monumental Ionic columns supporting a 2-story entrance porch.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1669, Apartments for Dr. Benjamin M. Rosebro, Address: 421-423 W. Grace St.,, 1910 (Folder 209)
      Drawn by: H. Parkhurst Atherton, Architect, 1208 Mutual Building, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: W. L. Ragland and Co.; Commissioned by: Dr. Benjamin M. Rosebro; Notes: Brick, 3-story over basement apartment house designed in the Colonial Revival style.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1458, Flat Building for Herbert Dalton, Address: S/S/ Park Ave. between Park St. and Allen Ave., 1910 (Folder 217)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: Quarles and Palmore; Commissioned by: H. S. Dalton; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 1121A, Apartment Building for Mrs. Barton H. Wise, Address: 923 W. Franklin St., 1910 (Folder 221)
      Drawn by: Noland & Baskervill, Architects, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: O. B. Slaughter; Commissioned by: Mrs. Barton H. Wise; Notes: The permit number and information on the outside of the drawing term this "Repairs to Brick Apartment House (Building 2 additional stories)." Apparently very soon after the original design was submitted and a building permit issued, the owner added two stories. The drawings reflect the as-built design.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2498, Brooke Apartments, W. C. Davis, Esq., Monument Ave., Address: S/S/ Monument Ave. between Allison and Addison Sts., 1911 (Folder 190)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: George D. Priddy; Commissioned by: W. Creed Davis; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2111, Store and Flats for Dr. Charles A. Labenberg and E. Raab, Address: SW corner 19th and Main Sts., 1911 (Folder 258)
      Drawn by: H. C. Linthicum, Jr., Architect; Contractor: L. C. Jenkins; Commissioned by: Dr. Charles A. Labenberg and E. Raab; Notes: 3 brick store buildings. 1st Floor = stores; 2nd Floor = flat/apt.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2185, Three Eight-Room Flats, Address: Corner of 13th and Leigh Sts., 1911 (Folder 263)
      Drawn by: Unsigned; Contractor: N/A; Commissioned by: E. P. Cathcart; Notes: One detached and two attached 2-story townhouses in the Colonial Revival style. Brick and stone construction.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2959, Apartment House, Eighth and Grace Streets, Henry S. Wallerstein, Owner, Pollard & Bagby, Promoters, Address: E. side Eighth St. between Franklin and Grace Sts., 1912 (Folder 124)
      Drawn by: Carneal & Johnston, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: W. A. Chesterman; Commissioned by: Henry S. Wallerstein; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2931, Apartment House for S. G. Meredith, Address: 3014 Monument Ave.,, 1912 (Folder 156)
      Drawn by: D. Wiley Anderson, Architect; Contractor: S. G. Meredith; Commissioned by: S. G. Meredith; Notes: Brick apartment building with 3 levels, two apartments on each. Apartment plan (front (Monument Ave. to back) = parlor, library, two chambers (bedrooms), dining room, kitchen, pantry, 2 full baths, and a servant room and bath. Front elevation is an exuberant D. Wiley Anderson American Renaissance composition including a flat roof with classical cornice. Levels are separated by balustrade porches supported by Corinthian columns. Double doors at center of each floor are topped with Palladian windows. Top floor windows are topped with flat arches and keystones.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2795, Flat Building for Mrs. Carrie Schwartz on S. E. Corner of Park Ave. & Mulberry St., Address: S/S Park Ave. between Mulberry and Robinson Sts., 1912 (Folder 122)
      Drawn by: E. A. & H. C. Smith, Architects; Contractor: George D. Priddy; Commissioned by: Mrs. Carrie Schwartz; Notes: A two-story and basement building. Upper two floors each have a parlor, library, dining room, kitchen, servants room, pantry, and butler's pantry. The plans call for sliding doors on principal rooms which are replaced by hinged doors n specifications.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 2751A, Plans for Remodeling a Residence into a Three-Story Apartment for W. A. Sorg, Address: 1100 Grove Ave.,, 1912 (Folder 135)
      Drawn by: Albert F. Huntt, 1107 E. Main Street, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: W. A. Dunn; Commissioned by: W. A. Sorg; Notes: 3 story residence remodeled into 3 flats. Plans for 2nd and 3rd floors are identical and show these rooms: stair hall, reception area, parlor, powder room, library, den, dining room, kitchen, 3 chambers (bedrooms), a servant room and service porch, plus a full bath.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3547, Westchester Apartments, Address: 1118 Grove Ave., 1913 (Folder 147)
      Drawn by: Marcus Hallett, Arc't., Mutual Building, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: W. H. Chesterman; Commissioned by: Westchester Apartment Co.; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3107, Monroe Terrace Apartments, Address: S/S/ Franklin St. between Laurel & Shafer St., 1913 (Folder 41)
      Drawn by: Alfred C. Bossom, Architect, 366 5th Avenue, N.Y. City; Contractor: Thos. J. Steene Co.; Commissioned by: City Investing Corp. (Monroe Terrace Corp.); Notes: Large blueprints on linen. Twelve-story apartment building. Extensive specifications.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3096, Apartments for Mr. G. N. Shuman, Address: 2346 Grace St. and East side Cedar St. [Davis Ave.?] between Broad & Grace St., 1913 (Folder 47)
      Drawn by: Unsigned; Contractor: O. C. Peers; Commissioned by: G. N. Shuman; Notes: Drawings are to be built in two locations. Three-story and basement brick apartment building with two, one-bedroom apartments on each floor. Each apartment also includes one room and half-bathroom for servants, a kitchen, bathroom, dining room, and parlor. Section drawing indicates a "dumb waiter shaft" from the first to third floors.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3166, Apartment for Mr. F.W. Brauer, Address: 2701 Kensington Ave. [corner Mulberry St.], 1913 (Folder 50)
      Drawn by: Chas. P. Duggins, Architect, 2523 Park Avenue; Contractor: Chas. F. Duggins; Commissioned by: F. W. Brauer; Notes: Three-story apartment building with two, two-bedroom apartments on each floor. The apartment in the front of the building is larger and includes a parlor and servant's room that the back apartment does not have. There is a solid wall between the two apartments that are served by separate entrances and stairs.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3090, Apartments for Mr. G. N. Shuman, Address: 2346 W. Grace St. [and East side Cedar St. between Broad and Grace St.], 1913 (Folder 40)
      Drawn by: Unsigned; Contractor: O. C. Peers; Commissioned by: G. N. Shuman; Notes: The specifications indicated that these drawings apply for two separate apartment buildings, one at 2346 West Grace St., the other on the east side of Cedar St. between Broad and Grace Sts. Specifications include hand-written changes. A three-story apartment building with one apartment on each floor. There is one shared servant's bathroom in the basement.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3115, Elm Apartment, Address: N. side Grove Ave. between Strawberry & Elm St., 1913 (Folder 52)
      Drawn by: Unsigned; Contractor: Davis and Archer; Commissioned by: Davis & Archer; Notes: Two-story apartment building with two flats on each floor.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3179, Richmond Home for Ladies, Address: N. side Stuart Ave. between Robinson and Mulberry Sts., 1913 (Folder 401)
      Drawn by: Charles K. Bryant, Architect, 410 American National Bank, Phone Mon. 2426, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: James Fox and Sons; Commissioned by: Richmond Home for Ladies; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3142, Apartment House for Mr. A. W. Bennett, Address: N. side Park Ave., between Allen Ave. & Meadow St., 1913 (Folder 62)
      Drawn by: W. Duncan Lee, Architect, 708 Travelers Building, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: W. A. [Chesterman]; Commissioned by: A. W. Bennett; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3108, Apartment House, Address: Corner Grace and Monroe St., 1913 (Folder 61)
      Drawn by: Grenville Temple Snelling, Marcus Hallett, Associated Arch'ts, 114 E. 28th St. N.Y. City, Mutual Bldg. Richmond, Va.; Contractor: N/A; Commissioned by: Unknown; Notes: Three-story and basement brick apartment building with metal Spanish tile roof. Six one and two-bedroom apartments on each floor. Two floor plans still have tracing paper comments and sketches laid on top.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3749, Three Story Apartment Building, Address: N. side Park Ave. between Davis and Addison Sts., 1914 (Folder 402)
      Drawn by: Asbury & Whitehurst, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Va.; Contractor: John T. Wilson and Co., Inc.; Commissioned by: Ellen J. Dance; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3804, Three Story Apartment Building, Address: W/S 4th St. between Main and Franklin Sts., 1914 (Folder 407)
      Drawn by: Davis Bros. (?); Contractor: Davis and Archer; Commissioned by: W. H. Davis, C. K. Archer, and W. H. Jenks; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3630, Apartment House - 1818 - 1820 Park Ave., Address: 1818 - 1820 Park Ave., 1914 (Folder 414)
      Drawn by: Asbury & Whitehurst, Architects & Engineers, #110 N. Seventh Street, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: Moore and Harry; Commissioned by: W. Ashby Jones, Sr.; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3596, Flat Building for Mr. J. Lee Davis, Address: W/S Mulberry St. bet Hanover & Stuart Ave., 1914 (Folder 619)
      Drawn by: Davis Bros.; Contractor: Davis Bros., Inc.; Commissioned by: J. Lee Davis; Notes: Two, two-story, attached Colonial Revival townhouses designed as flats.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3719, Brick Apartment Building, Address: N. side Monument Ave. between Robinson & Mulberry Sts., 1914 (Folder 412)
      Drawn by: E. D. Hobbs, Norfolk, Virginia; Contractor: E. D. Hobbs; Commissioned by: E. D. Hobbs; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3743, Three Story Apartment House, Address: N. side Park Ave. between Meadow St. and Allen Ave., 1914 (Folder 408)
      Drawn by: Asbury & Whitehurst, Architects & Engineers, Richmond, Virginia; Contractor: Wise Granite Construction Co.; Commissioned by: Mrs. E. B. Allen; Notes:
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3634, Porter St. Apartment House, Address: S/S 13th St. between Porter & Perry St., 1914 (Folder 624)
      Drawn by: I. T. Skinner; Contractor: E. R. Brown, Contr.; Commissioned by: E. R. Brown; Notes: Four story over a raised basement brick and stone apartment building with a first level corner store faced in plate glass. The building is styled with Classical and what appear to be Art Deco elements.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3750, Three Story Apartment Building, Address: E. side Davis Ave. between Monument and Park Aves., 1914 (Folder 399)
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3684, Flat Building for Mr. H. C. Brown, Address: 2205-7 Monument Ave., 1914 (Folder 622)
      Drawn by: I. T. Skinner; Contractor: Harvey C. Brown, Contractor; Commissioned by: Harvey C. Brown; Notes: Three story over raised basement brick and stone apartment building. Side entrances occur on each level and walk on to porches supported by Ionic and Corinthian columns.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: N/A, Apartment House Building, Address: Mulberry and Monument Ave., 1914 (Folder 607)
      Drawn by: E. D. Hobbs, Norfolk, Va.; Contractor: Richmond Structural Steel Co.; Commissioned by: N/A; Notes: Three level over raised basement apartment building with two story porch supported by Doric columns covering the central front entrance. A typical apartment building for this location.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 3605, The Hamilton Apartments, Address: E. side Elm St. between Floyd & Grove Ave., 1914 (Folder 613)
      Drawn by: Davis Bros. Inc.; Contractor: Davis Bros., Inc.; Commissioned by: Davis Bros, Inc.; Notes: Three story brick apartment building with flat roof and Classical cornice. The front, central doorway has transom and sidelights. It is topped with a two story, flat roof porch supported by giant Ionic columns.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 4288, Flat Building for P. J. Beattie, Address: S/S Stuart Ave. between Robinson and Mulberry, 1915 (Folder 359)
      Drawn by: I. T. Skinner; Contractor: W. S. Barnett; Commissioned by: P. J. Beattie; Notes: 2-story over basement brick house with full one-story porch. The tiled mansard roof is matched by the porch roof supported by Doric columns. Quoin corners and bracketed cornice complete this eclectic composition.
    - Apartments - Permit Number: 4118, The Davis Apartments, Address: 304 and 306 Mulberry St. between Hanover and Stuart Aves., 1915 (Folder 364)
      Drawn by: Davis Bros.; Contractor: Davis Bros.; Commissioned by: Davis Bros. Inc.; Notes: 3- story brick apartment building with flat roof and 2-story portico supported by colossal Ionic columns. According to Drew Carneal, a Fan District historian, the Davis brothers were quite successful because they could produce affordable housing by standardizing production methods and by aggressive marketing. No architect was ever listed on any plans that they submitted for city approval so it appears that they were skilled designers, again according to Carneal.